Guide to the Archibald J. Treat Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Archibald J. Treat papers
1883-1961
SC0511
Muybridge, Eadweard, 1830-1904
Stanford, Leland, 1824-1893.
Treat, Archibald J. (Archibald Jennings), 1864-1949.
0.25 Linear feet
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Unknown
Information about Access
None.
BIOGRAPHY
Archibald J. Treat was employed by the Central Pacific Rail Road in 1879 as an office boy and telegraph operator. He worked his way up to become secretary to Stephen T. Gage, who was assistant to Leland Stanford when Stanford was president of the CPRR. Treat also studied law while working for CPRR and was admitted to the California Bar in 1897. During the construction of Stanford University, Treat took photographs of the work in progress that were regularly sent to Leland Stanford to keep him informed.
SCOPE AND CONTENT
These papers pertain largely to Treat's association with Leland Stanford and the history of the University, and include correspondence, a notebook, his typescript reminiscences, and two letters by his daughter Laura Treat pertaining to her father.
Correspondents include Alice Hays, Timothy Hopkins, Herbert Hoover, David Starr Jordan, John B. McCarthy, Herbert C. Nash, and Burt Worthington. Subjects include the Stanford Mausoleum, Treat's photographs, business matters, and Eadweard Muybridge. These papers were originally included with the Leland Stanford papers, but have now been catalogued separately.
Access Terms
Hays, Alice Newman.; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964; Hopkins, Timothy, 1859-1937.; Jordan, David Starr, 1851-1931; McCarthy, John B.; Nash, Herbert C. (Herbert Charles), 1857-1902; Stanford University -- General subdivision--History.;; Worthington, Burt.; Photography--California.; Reminiscences
Collection Contents
- Outgoing letters, 1894, 1936-1941 (Folder 1)
  - to Wellington re the S.P. office and Chas. Stetson Wheeler, 1894 Nov 14
  - to Howard C. Tibbitts re Muybridge's experiment photographing horses at Palo Alto, John D. Isaacs, Muybridge's suit, Stanford's loss of the S.P.presidency, Timothy Hopkins, photographing sites for the University, 1936 Jan 20
  - to H. Hoover introducing himself and his reminiscences of the Stanfords, 1937 Aug 5
  - to J. H. Mitchell on Jordan's autobiography, Clark's biography of Stanford, Elliott's history, his photos of campus, and possible Indian grave site on campus, 1937Aug 31
  - to Alice Hays answering questions on Gustavus Hall, E. Narjot and the mausoleum, 1941 Feb 20
  - to Alice Hays answering question about a "terrace", 1941 Mar 8
  - to Alice Hays with more on the image in question, 1941 Mar 24
- Hays, Alice, letters, re: questions on Gustavus Hall, the Mausoleum, and one of Treat's photographs, 1937, 1941 (Folder 2)
- Hopkins, letters, 1892-1894 (Folder 3)
  - M. K. Hopkins (Mrs. Timothy?):, 1893 Dec 16 and 20
  - Timothy Hopkins: on Art Association, photographs he's bought, 1892 Aug 8
  - Timothy Hopkins: on various slides he wanted, 1894 May 25
- Hoover, Herbert, letter, 1937 (Folder 4)
- Jordan, David Starr, letter, re postponing a lecture, 1894 (Folder 5)
- McCarthy, John B, letters, Senator Stanford has received the photographs, 1887-1888 (Folder 6)
- Nash, Herbert C., letters, 1886-1891 (Folder 7)
  - photographs received and admired, 1886 Sep 24
  - on Nash's property transactions, Treat's difficulty with Ferguson, the Stanfords' appreciation of his photographs, 1888 Jan 30
  - on Treat's exhibit, political appointments (?), 1888 Dec 23
  - Stanfords in Canada, other personal news, 1890 Jan 7
  - Treat's sister visited, returning to California early March, President [Harrison] will probably visit there as guest of Stanford, 1891 Feb 10
- Olmsted, Frederick and Coolidge, Charles, letters (Folder 8)
  - Olmsted: received the photographs, 11/24/1886
  - Coolidge: received the photographs, 1/26/1888
- Worthington, Burt, letters, 1887 (Folder 9)
  - can't leave Sacramento because Mr. Stevens needs him, 6/10/1887
  - on his ambitions, 6/18/1887
- Notebook, partly in shorthand; includes short list of photographs taken, 1883-1885 (Folder 10)
- Treat, "The Stanfords and their Golden Key,", 1937; (2 ts copies) (Folder 11)
- Letters by Laura Treat, (A. Treat's daughter), 1952, 1961 (Folder 12)